# AHMED L. RASHED

Columbus, OH 43204 | 781-309-7560 | LinkedIn Profile | GitHub Portfolio | arashed07@gmail.com

## **Professional Summary**

Highly analytical and **process-oriented** data cruncher with over 10 years of experience in **data mining, statistical analysis, business intelligence gathering, trending, and benchmarking**. Created **ML models** on device telemetry to **pre-emptively classify CTQ** device failures before Final Test, *cutting rework times by 25%* and *increasing throughput by 10%*. Collaborated with test engineers to develop **ETL processes** to facilitate the **movement of data** between systems, **identifying patterns and insights** in the data, *reducing failure rates from 35% to 2%*.

## **Technical Skills**

Data Analytics: SQL, R Programming, Python, Tableau, Power BI (PowerQuery, DAX), Statistics, Hypothesis Testing.
Machine Learning: Linear/Logistic Regression, GridSearchCV, Random-Forest, XGBoost, Pickle, Decision-Trees.
Database & Project Management: EDA, ETL, SQL Server, Azure Data Studio, Google BigQuery, Agile, Scrum, JIRA, Git.
Business Intelligence: Collaboration, Continuous Improvement, Data Cleaning, Data Visualization, Data Presentation, Requirement Gathering, Problem Solving, Root-Cause Analysis, Turning Questions into Queries and Data into Insights.

### **Education & Certification**

Google Advanced Data Analytics Certificate

Google Data Analytics Certificate

Master of Arts - Physics - Bryn Mawr College

Bachelor of Science - Applied Physics - UMBC

## **Work Experience**

Data Analytics Consultant

#### **HENNY PENNY**

REMOTE- OH

11/2022 - 08/2023

Implemented **data hooks** in production test stand software to identify **key metrics** and **transform raw data** into meaningful, **actionable information** through **automated extraction** and **standardized reporting**.

- Created various **Python scripts** (numpy, pandas) using **SQL** (complex joins) to **extract and analyze** factory data, enhancing build quality and *saving Mfg engineers over 15 hours each week* in manual data manipulation.
- Collaborated with test engineers to develop **ETL processes** to facilitate the **movement of data** between systems, **identifying patterns and insights** in the data, *reducing failure rates from 35% to 2%*.

**Key Project:** Created python utility to extract and transform data from TestStand SQL database schema into flat CSV files.

- o **Tools Used:** SQL Server Management Studio, T-SQL, Python, PYODBC, Pandas.
- Results: Reduced script to single-file, used auto-py-to-exe to build a stand-alone executable file for users to download.

Quality Engineer Consultant

**GRANVILLE PHILLIPS** 

REMOTE-CO

09/2022 - 01/2023

Developed and integrated **data-driven metrics** into existing TestStand system to optimize Mfg process.

- Implemented **Python predictive analytics** (Scikit-learn) on test-unit data streams to **pre-emptively classify CTQ** device faults before Final Test, *cutting rework times by 25%* and *increasing throughput by 10%*.
- Deployed Mfg Statistical-Process-Control dashboards, improving first-pass-yield rates from 75% to 95%.

Principal Test Engineer

MKS INSTRUMENTS

Methuen, MA

03/2021 - 06/2022

Managed test station software projects, **ensuring quality and reliability** of software through comprehensive **testing and analysis**. Picked up **Python** and **SQL** on-the-job to drive enhanced **data analysis and visualization** for Tech Ops and Business Unit teams, creating compelling **data-driven reports** to upper management.

- Extracted and extrapolated Mfg data using **Python, SQL, and Excel** for monthly **quality reports**, *preventing over* \$50,000 in lost annual revenue by catching product quality defects BEFORE they leave the factory floor.
- Designed and built **statistical analysis models** on large data sets using **Azure Data Studio** that helped *reduce product rework and post-processing test-time by 15%.*

Senior Test Engineer MKS INSTRUMENTS Methuen, MA 09/2011 - 02/2021

Incorporated extensive upgrading and overhauling legacy product lines. Rerewrote test software architecture into **robust, data-driven, user-friendly applications**, *improving quality, reliability, and efficiency*.

- Connected **Tableau dashboards** to centralized **data-pipeline** for real-time production **data tracking**, *improving average time-to-bug-fixes by 20%* and *highlighting time-sinks* in factory workflows.
- Created **visually impactful dashboards** and **executive data visualizations** in Tableau to track production yields and failure modes, *saving test engineers over 10 hours* weekly in diagnostics and manual reporting.

# **Data Projects**

#### **TikTok Video Classification:**

TVC GitHub Link

12/2023

Exploratory data analysis to identify key metrics and trends to inform and drive appropriate marketing strategy.

- o Tools Used: Jupyter Notebook, Pandas, Pathlib, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn, Statsmodels.
- **Approach:** Developed machine-learning algorithm to predict whether videos presented claims or opinions to improve triaging process of videos for human review.
- Results: Both RandomForest and XGBoost architectures provided near-perfect models, but RandomForest had slightly higher accuracy and less processing, so it is the champion model. The most predictive features all were related to engagement levels generated by the video.

## **Sales Dashboard Report:**

SDR GitHub Link

11/2023

Demo dashboard mockup with downloaded SQL tables to show regional sales in Power BI Desktop.

- o **Tools Used:** Azure Data Studio, T-SQL, **Power BI**, Interactive Data Visualization.
- o **Approach:** Cleaned and sliced regional sales dataset with various **SQL queries**. Imported data to **PowerBI** with **PowerQuery** preprocessing to display **Key Process Indicators**. Created various **Slicers** for interactive filter views.

# **Housing Prediction Model:**

HPM GitHub Link

10/2023

Built and optimized a predictive regression model of housing prices with historical CA housing data.

- o Tools Used: Jupyter Notebook, Pandas, Pathlib, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Scikit-learn.
- Approach: Identified and removed outliers from the dataset. Created and modified the attributes of the data (feature engineering) to input into the model that is most relevant to predicting median-house-value. Tweaked and tuned Linear, GridSearchCV, and RandomForest Regressions to achieve 83% accurate predictions.
- o **Results:** Evaluated **RandomForest Regression** as the best overall model to predict median-house-value.

### **COVID-19 Retrospective:**

Cov19 GitHub Link

09/2023

Explored and visualized COVID's most affected countries, highest death rates, and fastest vaccination rates.

- Tools Used: Azure Data Studio, T-SQL, Tableau, Interactive Data Visualization.
- Approach: Explored and sliced the dataset with various SQL queries. Exported tables to CSV files for later importing to Tableau Desktop. After exporting and visualizing, we discovered an error in the calculations. New\_Vaccinations included both initial AND booster shots, resulting in Running\_Percent\_Vaccination going over 100%. Had to go back and reformat our query to use people\_vaccinated instead of new or total vaccinations.
- o **Results:** Published visualization to **Tableau Public LINK**.

## **Bike Sharing Analysis:**

BSA GitHub Link

07/2023

Exploratory data analysis to identify key metrics and trends to inform and drive appropriate marketing strategy.

- o **Tools Used:** R, **RStudio**, Data Extraction, **Data Cleaning**, Data Transforming, Data Interpretation.
- o **Approach:** Scraped the public data sets from the **AWS S3 bucket**. Loaded the CSV files with **fread()** and use **rbindlist()** to merge the individual data sets together. **Transformed data** by adding calculated columns. Generated **aggregate descriptive statistics** of categorical and numerical comparisons to identify A vs B populations.
- o **Results:** Minor **trends** in weekday vs weekend usage. Exported data for further time-series analysis.